<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Instruments on DIME-SHS</title>
    <link>https://dime-shs.sciencespo.fr/en/instruments/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Instruments on DIME-SHS</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>EN</language><atom:link href="https://dime-shs.sciencespo.fr/en/instruments/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>ELIPSS</title>
      <link>https://dime-shs.sciencespo.fr/en/instruments/elipss/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dime-shs.sciencespo.fr/en/instruments/elipss/</guid>
      <description>The DIME-QUANTI instrument, through its ELIPSS (Longitudinal Online Social Science Survey) panel, was a project that produces questionnaire-based surveys for the scientific community. It was based on a random sample (3000 individual) of the population resident in Metropolitan France, whose members had been supplied with an Internet connected touchscreen tablet on which to answer monthly surveys.
Browse ELIPSS website
 Objectives The purpose of Dime Quanti is to give the scientific community the means to produce data to the highest methodological standards.
Because the Elipss sample was randomly drawn, the academic surveys selected was able to achieve the benchmark criteria of statistical quality. In addition, the longitudinal nature of the survey was a strong feature, since there exist very few large-scale panel data for social science research.
A secondary objective of the Dime Quanti project was to develop methodological research, in particular by supporting innovative projects and experiments on survey design.
Finally, the documentation and dissemination of the data produced by the project was intended to promote their reuse and therefore to contribute to cumulative research processes.
Positioning Elipss is part of an international landscape of online panels intended for the scientific community. Use of the Internet has developed very quickly in the last 15 years in the field of marketing surveys and opinion polls, mainly because of the low costs and speed of collection possible with the web.
In a report on online surveys (Baker1, 2010), AAPOR (American Association for Public Opinion Research) draws attention to the significant biases in online “access” or “opt-in” panels as a way of conducting general population surveys. Although Internet access has grown rapidly since the early 2000s, part of the population is still off-line. In France in 2017, for example, 15% of the population were still without home Internet access. This lack of coverage automatically excludes part of the population from online surveys. Moreover, the use of access or opt-in panels with non-probabilistic samples casts doubt on their representativeness and on the extrapolation of results.
Nonetheless, the advantages of online surveys very quickly attracted social science research, in particular as a way to compensate for the drop in response rates in traditional surveys.
In order to overcome the biases flagged by AAPOR, an online panel needs to be constructed using a random sample of the population. This means employing an off-line method of recruitment (face-to-face or by telephone) to include people without Internet access and, if necessary, to provide them with an Internet connection (Das, Ester and Kaczmirek, 2011)2.
 In consequence, several initiatives emerged in the academic world: the LISS Panel developed by CentERdata at the University of Tilburg in the Netherlands and the Knowledge Panel in the United States were the first to use probabilistic sampling. France with ELIPSS and Germany with GESIS and GIP followed in 2011 (Blom et al., 2016)3. Other probabilistic panels designed for research were then set up in Norway, in Sweden, in Iceland, and in the UK.
The methods used to recruit and include people without Internet access differ between these national schemes. ELIPSS is original in that it gives all the panellists Internet access by supplying them with touchscreen tablets connected to the mobile network. The methodological advantage of this model is that it ensures that all the respondents have the same questionnaire format and that it avoids certain measurement distortions caused by different presentations of the questions.
Operation Submitted in response to calls for proposals, the surveys to be distributed to the ELIPSS panel are selected by the DIME Quanti Scientific and Technical Committee. The ELIPSS team then supports the research teams in the design of the questionnaire and manages the different stages of survey production: scheduling the questionnaire, testing, data collection via the ELIPSS application, field monitoring and reminders, and finally providing the project’s initiators with an exploitable data file.
After a maximum of one year’s exclusive access to the data for the teams that coproduce an ELIPSS survey, the data were added to the CDSP catalogue and were made available to the whole scientific community.
ELIPSS STC&amp;rsquo;s Members : Rémy Caveng, Joanie Cayouette-Remblière, François Denord, Céline Goffette, Anne Jadot (présidente), Dominique Joye, Cécile Lefèvre, Muriel Letrait, Pierre Mercklé, Gaël de Peretti, Élise Tenret, Loup Wolff, Sonja Zmerli. Also contributed to STC : François Beck, Michel Bozon, Bernard Denni, Julien Duval, Guy Michelat, Isabelle Récotillet et Karine van der Straeten.  Contributions By giving numerous research teams the means to conduct a survey, ELIPSS has collected an impressive array of rich data that sheds light on the most recent changes in social situations, practices and attitudes in France in a very diverse range of fields. Among the 80 resulting datasets, Dime Quanti has given rise to original interdisciplinary collaborations; the SHAMA survey, for example, essentially brought together architects and nutritionists to study the links between housing and obesity. The survey also stood out for the possibility of carrying out longitudinal surveys: the DYNAMOB project with 18 survey rounds conducted on the relationship to politics both during the election period and during the so-called ordinary period, or the annual survey on the evolution of living conditions carried out by the CDSP are the best examples of this. Finally, the data produced within the ELIPSS framework has sometimes been extremely timely, as demonstrated by the project Coping with covid-19.
The richness of these data makes it possible to undertake in-depth analyses of the dynamics running through French society, both because of the very large quantities of individual data collected on the practices, habits and attitudes of the panellists, and because of the longitudinal dimension of some of the surveys, whose questions are repeated several times at regular intervals in order to identify changes in behaviours and opinions at the most granular level.
Beyond the information they provide on French society, the numerous domains explored through the ELIPSS surveys make it possible to explore how this knowledge is constructed and the conditions in which it is produced. In fact, the use of online questionnaires administered to a panel on a touchscreen tablet supplied to the respondents makes it possible both to innovate methodologically, by developing and testing new ways of constructing questions and questionnaires for the general population, and to compare the data produced in this way with those obtained by other survey techniques, in France and in other countries.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>beQuali</title>
      <link>https://dime-shs.sciencespo.fr/en/instruments/bequali/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dime-shs.sciencespo.fr/en/instruments/bequali/</guid>
      <description>The beQuali/DIME-QUALI instrument is an archive of qualitative social science surveys available to the research and teaching community. The catalogue offers raw data, collected using qualitative methods (observations, interviews, focus groups, etc.), as well as additional analytical and contextual material on the research process, intended to facilitate the handling of the archive.
Browse beQuali website
 Objectives Designed to give France an archive of qualitative political science and sociology surveys equivalent to those of other European countries (UKDA, etc.), DIME-SHS be-Quali represents both a continuation and expansion of the work accomplished by the ANR’s réAnalyse project, which sought to test the possibilities of reanalysing French qualitative surveys.
In the same spirit, beQuali seeks to capitalise on existing and often under-analysed qualitative data, for purposes of secondary analysis or reanalysis, comparison or teaching. The preservation and dissemination of qualitative social science surveys also has a dimension of transparency, which reinforces the scientific character of qualitative research.
The retrospective documentation of the surveys and the development of exploration tools are at the heart of the project, intended to further understanding of the survey materials and, in particular, to improve the conditions of training in research through the use of real and tested data.
Positioning BeQuali fits into an international landscape of qualitative databanks created for the scientific community. Although beQuali is not comparable with the UK Data archive or with Harvard’s Henry A. Murray research archive (in terms of numbers of surveys or personnel), the instrument shares the same goal of making data available for reuse by researchers and of preserving social science materials.
Moreover, the beQuali survey archives has no equivalent in France and is therefore a pioneer in the hitherto empty French landscape of survey preservation and archiving (reports by Braibant1, 1996 ; Silberman2, 1999 ; Cribier and Feller3, 2003).
Aspiring to compare with international databanks and a frontrunner at national level, beQuali is undertaking a major task of documentation and re-contextualisation on the surveys in order to facilitate and encourage reuse.
Operation During the main period of the project, the surveys that form the catalogue were selected on different scientific or feasibility criteria by a scientific and technical committee (STC). The scientific community is invited to submit its projects through a call for proposals issued at least once a year.
The beQuali team was processing the materials of the selected surveys, uploading them to the beQuali site and referencing them on the download platform Quetelet Progedo Diffusion.
Part of beQuali’s role is to preserve research data and archive the surveys available at the National Higher Education IT Centre (CINES).
beQuali STC&amp;rsquo;s Members : Stéphanie Abrial, Lucie Bargel, Emilie Biland-Curinier, Jean-Gabriel Contamin, Baptiste Coulmont, Rémi Gallou, Odile Gaultier-Voituriez, Christophe Giraud, Gilles Laferté (président), Goulven Le Brech, Marie Loison-Leruste, Stéphane Loret, Gilles Pouchoulin, Anne Revillard, Joséphine Simonnot, Sara Tandar. Also contributed to STC: Bernard Bel, Antonio Casilli, Didier Demazière, Véronique Ginouvès, Christelle Hamel, Camille Hamidi, Dominique Le Roux, Nicolas Mariot, Brigitte Mazon, Jean-Luc Minel, Catherine Morel, Valérie Tesnière, Florence Weber.  Contributions Making the beQuali materials available publicises the work of the researchers who produced it and allows others to reuse it, in particular for the purpose of comparison or new interpretation (reanalysis, comparison, etc.). In addition, there are considerable benefits in sharing these materials for the teaching of qualitative methods.
As well as the raw material (interviews, preparatory documents, etc.), beQuali provides documentation that contextualises the research process: a “survey into the survey” is included in the form of a written report accompanied by audio extracts of interviews with the researchers who conducted the surveys.
Although it is still too soon to draw definitive conclusions about what lessons can be learned from this experiment in terms of research and teaching, the first research reuses show the benefits that can arise from giving these materials a second life. For example, revisiting a survey4 on the political representations of the French 30 years on made it possible to enrich the original typology by reintegrating sections of the material that could not be included at the time. Another example, a piece of research on parliamentarians in France and in Germany was substantially broadened by the inclusion of interviews originating in another piece of research conducted a few years earlier.
Beyond this, the availability of these materials offers new pedagogical possibilities for a growing number of teachers wishing to use alternative sources to tackle methodological issues differently, as well as the big questions of sociology or political science. In this sense, beQuali is helping to provide the scientific community with the resources needed for genuine methodological research to develop in France, comparable with the situation that already prevails, for example, in the Anglo-Saxon world.
Sustainability At the end of the Dime-SHS project, beQuali&amp;rsquo;s expertise is being put to good use in order to continue developing the catalog of surveys, both in number and in terms of the disciplines and methods used (surveys based on ethnographic observations, mixed quantitative-quali surveys, etc.).
Within the context of opening up research data and with a desire to broaden the services offered to the scientific community, beQuali offers support for projects in progress (participation in the implementation of data management plans). The objective is to help research teams manage the data they produce by anticipating their possible availability on the beQuali survey database. It is also a matter of initiating best practices in terms of documentation, storage and archiving and thus making these surveys more easily and quickly communicable.
At the same time, beQuali continues to promote use of the available corpora. Therefore, as part of the action plan for the end of Equipex, a self-training module for teaching methods and a tool for filtering interview transcripts according to the sociographic properties of the speakers has been incorporated into the tool. In the future, other resources will be developed, such as &amp;ldquo;teaching kits&amp;rdquo; for courses on qualitative methods.
 Braibant Report, 1996 ↩ Silberman Report, 1999 ↩ Cribier and Feller Report, 2003 ↩ Types idéologiques et classe résiduelle dans l’enquête d&amp;rsquo;Étienne Schweisguth : Les Français et la politique, 1982-1988.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dime Web</title>
      <link>https://dime-shs.sciencespo.fr/en/instruments/dime-web/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dime-shs.sciencespo.fr/en/instruments/dime-web/</guid>
      <description>The DIME-Web instrument is a team of one to three engineers which supports Social Science research projects in the development and use of digital methods to exploit the web as a survey medium. In particular, it is used to collect, enhance, clean up, visualise and analyse data from digital traces accessible online.
Browse Dime Web website
 Objectives The purpose of DIME-Web was to equip the Social Science world to exploit digital traces left on the web. The instrument was addressing different research populations with different types of approaches and timeframes: advice in the choice and use of digital methods, identification of sources available on the web, end-to-end development of reusable, free and open source generic tools, pedagogical or academic training, methodological support, one-off support in an afternoon workshop, support throughout a multi-year research project.
To these ends, the instrument developed and supplied a whole battery of tools in the form of free open source software, which can be used to collect data from across the web with crawlers such as Hyphe, or from targeted platforms such as Twitter using the Gazouilloire software, for cleaning, enhancement or classification, or else for visualisation, exploration and study, notably from the perspective of network analysis. Free and open source, these tools can not only be freely downloaded, installed and re-engineered by third parties, but many of them can be run directly online, for example utilities like Table2Net, ScienceScape, CatWalk or SeeAlsology.
The most ambitious of Dime Web tools is the Hyphe web crawler, which helps users in building, curating and categorizing qualitative web corpora of hypertext links between entities grouped quantitatively on the web. Both highly technical and user friendly, Hyphe offers students and researchers in the social sciences an exploratory and quali-quantitative method of studying communities of interest relating to their research fields. It is currently used by researchers in several European countries and in the Americas.
Positioning The DIME-Web team was standing at the intersection of the fields of methodological research and digital methods in the social sciences. As well as supporting researchers in their methodology, it offered them its skills in network analysis and web archiving, as well as in controversy analysis inspired by Bruno Latour’s Actor Network Theory (ANT). The members of the operational team have authored or co-authored some fifteen academic publications, including an article on PlosOne in 2015 about the ForceAtlas2 network spatialisation algorithm implemented in the Gephi software, as well as a number of papers introducing Hyphe, notably at the ICWSM 2016 and FOSDEM 2018 conferences.
The link with the local research and innovation environment was essentially coming through technology exchange. The free and open source technologies used and/or developed by DIME-Web and more broadly by the medialab, were also being developed by an ecosystem of specialists united by questions relating to networks and data visualisation. Private sector entities were also sometimes interested in training courses on these technologies.
The fields that have historically been most receptive to such work were web studies, social network analysis and controversy mapping. The instrument attracted a wide range of academic and university users in France, but also abroad, especially in a number of European countries where the medialab has formed ties in the digital methods community: Richard Rogers’ Digital Methods Initiative de Richard Rogers) in Amsterdam, the Tantlab in Copenhagen, King’s College in London… Since 2011, therefore, numerous training courses and papers, notably on Hyphe, have been delivered in different countries in Europe and beyond, and DIME-Web tools have been implemented internally in different universities in England, Denmark, the United States.
Operation DIME-Web’s operational team essentially was relying on two engineers recruited in 2011 and 2012, who pooled their working time with the Sciences Po medialab, an approach that notably provides access to more varied skills (designers, expert JavaScript developers, researchers…).
Supporting research projects encompasses different realities, which demand different levels of input. One-off requests for help, which are also often requests for guidance, were dealt with at Sciences Po’s monthly open-doors workshop at the medialab. This is often the occasion for initial contacts, which may then develop into a paying service. DIME-Web also gives courses to groups of researchers and PhD candidates, either in a project support role, or independently, for example at summer schools. Since 2014, both members and nonmembers of the Equipex consortium have been charged a fee for access to the facility for support, training or joint research development, which therefore helps to finance the development of the generic tools.
A specific DIME-Web Scientific and Technical Committee (STC) was monitoring the project selection process and the orientation of the programme, through one annual face-to-face meeting and ongoing digital interchanges. Between 2014 and 2020, selection and support for small projects that require rapid response without costly developments (by contrast with the bigger projects) have been delegated to the operational team and the STC’s role is confined to annual oversight.
Dime Web STC’s members:
 Dominique Cardon, Dana Diminescu, Guilhem Fouetillou, Dominique Goux, Delphine Lagarde, Raphaël Laurent, Olivier Martin, Clément Oury, Franck Rebillard, Roxane Silberman, Jérôme Thièvre Tommaso Venturini.   Contributions Dime Web has accompanied more than twenty research projects carried out by teams from a wide range of backgrounds throughout the duration of the project, from sociology to economics and political science. For example, in the RiscoVac and PerseVac projects, the Web tool has helped in studying the controversies surrounding vaccines online, by measuring and evaluating the presence and influence of anti-vaccine actors on the web and social networks. Similarly, with the economists of the SoWell project for example, the Dime Web team assisted in the collection and analysis of search engine usage data in order to model well-being in different countries. In an entirely different vein, the ComIngGen project has benefited from the support of the instrument to study the extent to which discussion on the web has been able to both relay and fuel the debates around biotechnology and the public policies surrounding it.
Between 2011 and 2020, the Web tool has also led to the creation of a number of digital tools dedicated to the social sciences and freely available for anyone to use, indirectly supporting a wide range of users in France and abroad, in both the academic and pedagogical worlds, as well as in journalistic and associative circles.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
